Three years ago, I was supposed to get married.
三年前，我本來要結婚
But I fell for someone else.
但是我喜歡上了別人
It was him.
那就是他
He was my student.
他是我的學生
I'm the only one still where I was,
只有我還在原地踏步
unable to move forward.
無法向前邁進
Let's forget.
忘了吧
I'll help you forget.
我來幫你忘記她
You have moved forward.
妳已經前進了
Ms. Suenaga.
末永老師
You're moving forward.
妳已經向前走了
Slowly, one step at a time, you're moving forward.
慢慢地、一步步地向著前方前進
If you're still hung up on Hijiri, and just using me…
如果你還是想著小聖，只是利用我…
Treating me like some substitute.
當我是備胎
I can't take it.
我無法接受
It's okay.
沒關係
Ms. Chizuru, your mouth.
千鶴老師，妳的嘴巴
Your mouth.
妳的嘴巴
Ah, yeah.
啊，是喔
Wait, so you're saying that despite knowing everything about your past,
等一下，也就是說 即使知道妳過去的一切
Mr. Nogami still hugged you saying it was okay?
野上老師還是抱緊妳說沒關係嗎？
I know I can't take advantage of his kindness.
我知道我不能接受他的好意
But I was relieved.
但我鬆了一口氣
It made me think that maybe it's okay for me to stay here.
讓我覺得自己可以 繼續像這樣待在這裡
I'm relieved too.
我也鬆了一口氣
It's been three years since we've talked about your love life. It's a good match.
已經三年沒聽妳 提起感情事了，這是個良緣
No, please.
不是那樣的啦，拜託
Mr. Nogami hasn't acted any differently since then.
因為後來野上老師舉止也很一般
We did grab a bite to eat together once at the next station over.
雖然有去鄰鎮吃過一次飯
Then I'll be your matchmaker.
那我來幫你們牽線
That's okay.
不用啦
I'm kidding.
開玩笑的啦
Listen, Hijiri.
聽好，聖
Your next boyfriend will probably be the man you marry.
下一個男朋友大概就是結婚對象了
So wish for the best and go for it. Just ask him out yourself!
妳要朝好的方向想做好準備進攻 妳要主動邀他出去！
Take the lead and ask him out. Hurry!
妳要積極地主動邀他出去，快點！
Don't run. Don't fall.
不要跑，別跌倒了
Good morning.
早安
Ow…
好痛…
Hey!
喂！
Tachibana?
橘同學？
-Tachibana! -Are you okay?
-橘同學！ -橘同學，妳還好嗎？
-You okay?
-沒事吧？ -妳還好嗎？
-Is it your stomach? -Are you alright?
-肚子痛嗎？
-Nogami, get the school nurse. -Okay.
-野上，你去保健室叫護士 -是
Let me grab your bag for you.
橘同學，我來拿妳的書包吧
-Malnutrition? -And the resulting anemia.
-營養不良？ -好像有一點貧血
There are more and more cases.
最近越來越多宗呢
They get enough calories, but not nutrition.
雖然熱量足夠，但營養不良
Where's her mother?
她媽媽呢？
She said she was working all weekend.
她說週末一直都在工作
No way, I bet she was with a guy.
騙誰啊，八成又是和男人在一起
No answer.
她沒接
But I left a message.
我有留言了
I heard a rumor she got dumped and is taking it badly.
聽說她最近跟男友分手，情緒很糟糕
There are women like that who need a man to keep her life stable.
那種女人沒男人的話 日子就無法穩定下來
What a mess.
真傷腦筋
You prioritize your kid, obviously!
必須要把孩子放在第一位啊！
Anyway, I'll stay behind and wait for her mother to pick her up.
總之，今天我會留下來 等到她母親來接她
-Please do. -I'll stay with you.
-拜託了 -我也一起
-Thanks. -No problem.
-那麻煩了 -好的
Excuse me.
打擾了
What're you reading?
妳在看什麼？
Let me see.
也讓老師看看吧
It's been three years now.
自那以後已經過了三年了
I ripped them apart
我拼命將他們分開
to get my little boy back.
讓他變回普通的孩子
But now he hates me, and won't even see me.
結果現在被他討厭，甚至連我都不見
If you go, there's no coming back.
你去了就回不來了
I'm back.
我回來了
You're looking again.
社長，妳又在看了
Come on, you need to let this go.
不行喔，這樣鑽牛角尖對妳不好
Take deep breaths.
來深呼吸吧
What if Akira finds out about her?
如果阿晶知道這件事會怎麼樣？
And breathe out.
吐氣
He's finally settled down, if he gets dragged back in again,
他好不容易才安定下來 萬一又變回像以前那麼奇怪
there's no coming back.
那就無法挽救了
Akira's not going to find out, I'd never tell him.
阿晶不知道啦，我也絕對不會說
I'll go see Ms. Shioya.
我去找鹽谷老師
From his junior high school?
國中那個鹽谷老師嗎？
I'm going to ask if the school knows about this.
我去問她學校那邊知不知道這件事
Sorry for the short notice, and for not contacting you.
抱歉突然跑來，沒有聯絡妳
I've been working nonstop.
最近一直都在打工
You're working that much?
你打工排這麼滿啊？
I don't want my mom paying for me.
我想儘量不讓我媽付錢
What's your job again?
你現在在做什麼打工？
Bread factory.
麵包工廠
I brand the bread after they're done baking.
在剛烤好的麵包上 壓上“粒餡”印章的工作
Brand?
粒餡？
-That's funny. -Not really.
-好好笑 -才沒有
I want to hold hands.
我想牽手
Sorry about before.
對不起，那個時候
For not going through with it.
結果沒有做到最後
You know, I don't think I was ready.
那時我沒做好心理準備
I just went for it, but I didn't know what you were thinking
幾乎是一時情急 但我不知道你在想什麼
or how you felt about me. I still don't know, so--
還是搞不太懂你是怎麼看我的 我還是不懂，所以…
What?
什麼？
Damn.
不妙
I like this.
好像會上癮
What?
什麼？
Can I get used to this?
我可以就這樣上癮嗎？
Can we say that we're dating?
我可以當作我們在交往了嗎？
DON'T CRY ANYMORE, KURIZURA
（《別哭了，栗倉》）
If her mother can't come get her, Ayano can come stay with me.
如果她不來接孩子 今天就先讓彩乃住在我家
That'd be great!
那太好了
I'm glad you were here.
幸好有妳在
Please, if I were alone, I think I would've just panicked.
不，我才是 只有我一個人肯定會手忙腳亂
It's nothing.
不會啦
I'm glad you're the head teacher.
還好班導是你
Oh, please.
哪裡
Um.
那個
Come to think of it, we haven't
說起來
talked about it.
我們還沒把話說完
If…
如果…
If you'd like…
如果妳不嫌棄…
No, now's not the time.
不，果然不適合現在說
But we don't get to talk much like this.
可是很少有這樣的機會說話
Um…
那個…
I'm sorry I'm late.
對不起，我太晚來了
I couldn't get out of work.
工作一直抽不開身
No one's on the register's now.
現在沒人顧收銀呢
I called your work.
我打電話去問過妳工作地點了
The manager said you had the day off today.
店長說妳今天請假
Actually, I wasn't feeling well.
其實我身體不太舒服
I was resting at home.
人在家裡休息
I spoke to Mr. Nogami.
我跟野上老師討論過了
If this happens again,
如果再次發生這樣的事
your parents…
妳的父母…
-My parents? -In case something happens to Ayano.
-我的父母？ -我們很擔心彩乃發生什麼事
We could have her grandparents--
這種情況就會請爺爺或奶奶來…
Please stop.
不要告訴他們
I've cut ties with my parents.
我跟父母斷絕關係了
I'm only staying in their home, but that's all.
他們只是借我房子住，就這樣而已
We're no contact.
完全沒有往來了
Did you call them already?
妳該不會已經通知他們了吧？
No, not yet.
不，目前還沒有
-But if-- -If you overstep…
-但如果… -如果妳敢擅自決定
I'll reveal your secret.
我也會抖出妳的事
You have a secret, don't you?
妳有不可告人的秘密，是吧？
I don't know what you're talking about.
妳在說什麼？
I know about it.
我都知道喔
Mom!
媽媽！
Ayano, I'm sorry I'm late!
彩乃，對不起，我來晚了！
Here.
給妳
Clip.
髮夾
Ms. Tachibana, you had me worried.
橘小姐，我們都很擔心她喔
-I'm sorry, Mr. Nogami. -We're fine.
-野上老師，實在很對不起 -我們倒是沒關係
But I think your daughter was missing you.
但我想妳女兒肯定很想妳
Considering her health as well.
也有健康方面的問題
Perhaps you should rely on your parents--
妳應該多仰賴妳父母…
No, I promise not to cause any worry again.
不，我絕不會再讓你們擔心
-Just please don't involve them. -But--
-請不要告訴他們 -可是…
If you involve them, they'll take Ayano from me.
如果扯到我父母，彩乃就會被帶走
I may not be a good mother, but I love Ayano.
雖然我是個糟糕的母親 可是我很愛彩乃
You understand, don't you?
你們能諒解吧？
Ms. Suenaga?
末永老師？
I'm sure Ayano is tired,
我想彩乃也累了
so I think it's best
最好
if she took her home for today.
先回家休息吧
Okay.
好的
But if something happens again,
不過若又發生什麼事
I will be contacting your parents.
我一定會聯絡妳的父母
Let's go, Ayano.
走吧，彩乃
-Thanks, Akira. -Sure.
-謝謝，阿晶 -好的
-I'm off then. -Have a good day.
-我出去了 -慢走
Kokonoe.
九重
-Yo. -Long time, cadet.
-喲 -好久不見，棒球小子
Like I said, Mr. Joffe, this is just my hairstyle.
喬飛先生，這只是我的髮型啦
What's up?
怎麼了？
-Iwasaki? -Yeah.
-岩崎？ -是
We're going out, why do you ask?
我們在交往啊，怎麼了？
What, you came all this way to ask me?
幹嘛？你特地跑來問這種事嗎？
Do you like Iwasaki?
你喜歡岩崎嗎？
I do.
喜歡啊
We're not kids anymore, there's different levels of like.
我們已經不是小孩了 喜歡有分很多種
What kind of like is it?
你的喜歡是屬於哪一種？
I don't have to see the scary part of myself.
能夠不去面對可怕的自己
Why now?
為什麼現在又出現？
Kuroiwa's mom found this.
聽說是黑岩的媽媽發現的
Really?
是嗎？
Ebihara's little brother happened to see her talking to the teachers.
海老原的弟弟碰巧在學校聽見 她跟老師們在講這件事
-Did you tell Kuroiwa? -No.
-黑岩知道嗎？ -我沒說
I haven't, but…
雖然沒告訴他，但…
Honestly, I'm torn.
說實在的，我很猶豫
But I wanted to talk to you about it first.
不過在那之前，得先讓妳知道
Damn it, stay away.
討厭，不要過來啦
It's too late.
事到如今都太遲了
No, we have to keep it secret.
不能說喔，要瞞著他
It's finished if he sees her.
他們如果見面就全完了
His feelings will come back.
黑岩立刻就會回去喜歡她
You think so?
妳覺得會嗎？
I told you not to get involved with him.
所以我早就說過別選他了
But it's also not fair to keep this from him, right?
但是瞞著他是不公平的吧？
I mean, he might not think anything of it.
搞不好他會一笑置之啊
I'm a high school girl now, we've also hooked up.
我可是貨真價實的女高中生喔 我們也一起過夜了
You think I'd lose to the memory of some teacher pushing 30?
你們覺得我會輸給 快三十歲的女老師的回憶嗎？
I'd be careful, men don't have to have feelings to handle a girl.
我是妳的話會小心一點 男人就算不喜歡也能應對
I want to fight on even ground.
我想在公平的狀態下一決勝負
Then you tell him.
那妳自己告訴他
Do whatever feels right. You're his girlfriend after all.
做個了結吧，畢竟妳是他女友
I need to go pee.
我去趟廁所
What is it, Yu?
妳怎麼了，小優？
We had this teacher Ms. Suenaga.
有一個叫末永的老師
Rumor is that she messed around with a student.
大家都說她搞上學生
So they found her.
有人找到她啦
Okay, we'll be making the flowers for the recital.
好了，接下來要做發表會要用的花
You two, listen to Mr. Nogami!
那邊的同學，聽老師說話
Hey.
喂
Stop fooling around.
不要再玩了
Sit down.
坐下
-Take a seat. -Sit down.
-坐好 -坐下
We'll be making flowers like these.
就是要做這樣的花
Those are so good, Ms. Hijiri.
好漂亮，老師
-You made them? -Yes.
-是妳做的嗎？ -是啊
Each of you will make three.
每個人請做三朵
-What's that? -A star fish?
-那是什麼？ -海星？
A crushed can?
壓扁的鋁罐？
They're clearly flowers!
怎麼看都是花吧！
Terrible!
很難看！
All of you sit down.
都回去坐好
Okay, I was wrong.
好啦，是老師不會
Do you have the report on the renovation project?
裝修工程的報告書呢？
I'm almost done.
快要完成了
Um, so like,
那個，我現在
I totally understand girls who need to ask what their relationship status is.
好像能夠體會女生忍不住想確認 我們現在是什麼關係的感覺
What?
什麼？
I'm sorry.
對不起
Damn it.
糟糕
Could you take me out to Roppongi?
去六本木通可以嗎？
W-What?
什…什麼？
What?
什麼？
Where are we going?
我們要去哪？
I was going to go home and cool down.
我要回家冷靜一下
The Mongols say to strike while the iron is hot.
蒙古人常說打鐵要趁熱
They say that here too.
日本人也是這麼說
I don't want my clothes to wrinkle.
我不想衣服留下皺折
So lend me something to wear.
借我幾件你的衣服
Okay.
好的
-Are you free tonight? -Why?
-妳今天晚上有空嗎？ -幹嘛？
I can lend you clothes again.
我可以再借妳衣服
Your t-shirt was lame.
你在家穿的T恤很醜
Sorry, I don't know fashion.
對不起，我不懂流行
Sometimes your suit is lame too.
西裝有時也不合身
Well, I get whatever's on sale.
我看到什麼在打折就買
But I like that about you.
但我就喜歡你這點
That's good.
太好了
-Make sure to add pictures to the report. -Yes, ma'am.
-報告書要加上照片 -是
The digital camera…
數位相機…
I forgot to copy the data from the camera I returned.
我還給妳的數位相機 裡面的資料還沒有備份
From your boyfriend?
是男友嗎？
Hello.
妳們好
Were you out shopping?
橘同學，妳們去買東西嗎？
Don't worry, I'm cooking for her.
放心吧，我有好好煮飯
Okay, that's good.
是，那就好了
It's so awful.
真是討厭
Small towns like this are always looking for something to talk about.
在這種小村子，謠言總是滿天飛
I can't even shop in peace.
去買東西就會被看籃子裡的東西
It's suffocating.
簡直喘不過氣
But I hope
不過我希望
I can count on you to be on my side.
老師能站在我這邊喔
Let's go, Ayano.
走吧，彩乃
Ms. Suenaga.
末永老師
I want everyone's names on a screen after the play ends.
當天表演結束後 我想在螢幕上秀出大家的名字
Then we could take pictures of rehearsals.
那麼也拍下練習的照片吧
Oh, yes, we can put those up too.
好主意，一起播放吧
Yes.
好的
Thanks for walking me home.
謝謝你送我回來
It's nothing, it's on the way.
哪裡，我剛好順路
Um…
那個…
-The other day… -Huh?
-那天… -嗯？
-A stink bug. It's a stink bug. -What?
-是椿象… -什麼？
-Is it a stink bug? -Yeah.
-是椿象嗎？ -是啊
-What? -It stinks.
-什麼？ -好臭
Oh, crap!
糟糕！
It stinks!
好臭！
Sorry, maybe we can talk about this another time.
對不起，下次再把話說完吧
Okay.
好的
I'm sorry.
不好意思
Good night.
晚安
It stinks.
好臭
It really stinks.
真的好臭
Over there?
那邊嗎？
Yeah.
是
-Do I have hair stinking out? -No.
-我頭髮沒綁好嗎？ -沒有
Your feet look painful.
妳的腳好像很痛
Does it hurt?
很痛嗎？
I'm okay.
沒事啦
Let's go.
走吧
Hold on.
等一下
Then you tell him.
那妳自己告訴他
Do whatever feels right. You're his girlfriend after all.
做個了結吧，畢竟妳是他女友
Here.
給妳
Thanks.
謝謝
How much?
多少錢？
Forget it, it's my treat.
不用了，我請妳
Thanks.
謝謝
-Hello? -It's me, Yu.
-喂？ -我是小優
Wanna know where Suenaga is?
你想知道末永在哪裡嗎？
What?
什麼？
So you don't know, huh?
你果然不知道吧？
It was going around. So I wondered if you'd heard.
我聽到消息，猜想你大概不知道吧
I saw Runa whispering about it with her friends.
上次也看到瑠奈他們在偷偷討論
I feel sorry that they're keeping you in the dark.
你真可憐，被蒙在鼓裡
FYI, Suenaga is still teaching.
順帶一提，末永還在當老師
I'll send you a picture. Anyway, bye.
總之我現在傳照片給你，掰啦
What's up?
怎麼了？
KOMIYA DAI-ICHI ELEMENTARY
（小宮第一小學）
I was gonna tell you about this today.
我本來打算今天告訴你
But, you know,
但是
I didn't get a chance yet.
一直找不到好時機
Kuroiwa?
黑岩？
I'll be there soon, thank you for the camera.
我快到了，麻煩妳拿相機給我了
Camera…
相機…
The school?
那個學校？
KOMIYA DAI-ICHI ELEMENTARY
（小宮第一小學）
Kuroiwa?
黑岩同學？
Is that you?
是你嗎？
Remember me?
記得我嗎？
I guess not.
不記得啦
You're her…
你是老師的…
You came to see Hijiri? I'm here to see her too.
你來找聖嗎？我正好也要來看她
Those three years really made a difference.
過了三年變化真大啊
What?
什麼？
Nothing.
沒什麼
Huh?
嗯？
You're leaving?
你要走了嗎？
She didn't exactly invite me.
她並沒有叫我來
So why'd you come?
那你來幹嘛？
I just learned that she was here today.
剛才我聽說她在這裡
So I rushed here.
立刻就跑來了
Could you stay away from Hijiri?
你可以別再糾纏聖了嗎？
Hijiri
聖
has me.
還有我
Oh, right.
哦，也是
Makes sense.
也對
It seems yet again, I was wrong about a lot of things.
我好像又搞錯了很多事
I'll leave.
我要走了
Found it.
找到了
Tachibana.
橘同學
What's wrong?
怎麼啦？
Where's your mom?
妳媽媽呢？
Hey.
嘿
What's your favorite pasta dish?
妳喜歡吃哪一種義大利麵？
MR. PICTURE AND MR. WORD
（《圖片先生和字先生》）
Sorry, I know it's not the carbonara you like,
對不起，雖然不是 妳喜歡吃的培根蛋黃義大利麵
but it's my quick and easy mushroom pasta I make all the time.
這是老師很常做的 隨意快炒香菇義大利麵
Dig in.
請用
Here.
來
Let's eat.
我開動了
It's yummy.
好好吃
You like it?
好吃嗎？
MS. TACHIBANA, I'M SORRY FOR LEAVING THIS NOTE
（橘小姐，很抱歉留下這張字條）
-Who's she? -One of my students.
-那孩子是誰？ -她是我班上的一個學生
Her mom wasn't home when she got back from the library,
她從圖書館回家時，媽媽剛好不在家
and she got locked out.
因此進不了家
Being a teacher sounds tough.
當老師真辛苦
Here.
這個
Right.
對喔
Good, it's all here.
果然在裡面
I'm saved!
得救了
-Thanks. -No problem.
-謝啦 -沒問題啦
I just learned that she was here today. So I rushed here.
剛才我聽說她在這裡，立刻就跑來了
Hey, so…
那個…
I need to get back to work.
我得趕快回去工作了
-Thanks. -Sure.
-謝啦 -沒事
Later, Hijiri.
再見，聖
Ms. Suenaga, what a wonderful boyfriend you have.
老師，原來妳有那麼棒的男友啊
He seemed very metropolitan.
是個很都會感的帥哥呢
Why are you keeping him secret?
為什麼要隱瞞呢？
He's just an old friend.
他只是我的老朋友
Anyway, Ayano--
比起這個，彩乃她…
She forgot to take her key with her.
她忘了帶鑰匙
But it's worrying when this keeps happening.
如果發生好幾次這樣的事 這樣還是很讓人擔心
It's just a misunderstanding, no big deal.
只是剛好沒遇到，請不要大驚小怪
You don't want people talking either, do you?
妳也不想被說閒話吧？
Mom.
媽媽
Ayano, sorry I'm late.
彩乃，對不起，我太晚回來了
Are you okay? Sorry I was late.
妳還好嗎？對不起，這麼晚來
Let's go.
走吧
Did you eat?
妳有吃東西嗎？
Want me to cook you something?
要不要媽媽做給妳吃？
I got the pictures right away.
我立刻拿到照片了
Here you go.
來
Which means you met Hijiri.
這麼說你去見小聖了
Not just her, but him too.
不只聖，還見到他了
Him?
他？
So, did you meet her?
所以，你見到她了嗎？
Or didn't you?
還是沒見到呢？
Then
不然
at least answer this.
至少回答我這個問題
Do you like me?
你喜歡我嗎？
Even just
即使
a little?
只有一點點？
past tense?
是過去式？
Runa!
瑠奈！
Long time no see!
好久不見！
You're dating Akira?
妳在跟阿晶交往嗎？
That's what I heard from your mother Sayuri.
我聽妳媽媽小百合說了
I had no idea.
我都不知道
It's amazing.
真的很不敢置信
Huh?
嗯？
When I call him, he would come over.
一通電話黑岩就會來
We'd spend time alone.
能夠兩人獨處
He'd be kind to me.
他很溫柔對待我
Even if it was just his way of handling me.
就算這些事情都只是單純的應對
Handling?
應對？
What do you mean?
妳在說什麼？
But…
可是…
If…
如果…
Suenaga steals him again…
末永再次搶走他的話…
You mean that Suenaga?
妳是說那個末永嗎？
They haven't met, have they?
他們兩個該不會見到面了吧？
That's a bit of a gray area.
灰色地帶
-What? -Gray area?
-什麼？ -灰色地帶？
It seems like he wasn't able to meet her.
最後好像沒見到
But he headed straight for her when he found out where she was.
但是他一知道她的所在地 就飛奔過去了
In a second.
立刻
It's yummy.
好好吃
If you involve them, they'll take Ayano from me.
如果扯到我父母，彩乃就會被帶走
You don't want people talking either, do you?
妳也不想被說閒話吧？
So basically, when the boy showed up to see Hijiri--
所以就是說，當那男孩來見小聖時…
He's a young man now, basically an adult.
已經是成年人了，不對，快成年
You acted like you married her and turned him away.
假裝你們好像結婚了，把他趕回去
He just assumed.
是他自己誤會
And you didn't tell Hijiri anything on top of that.
而且你還沒告訴小聖
I didn't have time.
因為沒時間說
I'm going home.
我要回家了
What? Why?
怎麼了？為什麼？
Hey, hold on.
喂，等一下啦
What is it?
怎麼了？
Since when do you talk to me like that?
你什麼時候這樣和我說話了？
Wait, are you jealous?
等一下，難道說妳吃醋了？
What?
什麼？
Because I went to see Hijiri and turned him away?
因為我去找聖，把他趕回去嗎？
You think I'm not over her?
所以妳覺得我還對聖有留戀嗎？
Don't be cocky.
少得意忘形了
You don't need to worry.
沒必要擔心啦
But, it's just…
不過，我只是…
Just?
只是？
What?
什麼？
In that moment,
那一刻
the feeling I felt when I saw him
我看到他時想到的是
was unforgiving.
無法原諒
If they meet again, and everyone says that their love is real.
若是他們又見面了 所有人認為這段戀情是真愛
That it's destiny.
是命中註定
I can't forgive it.
那我無法原諒
Hijiri was wrong.
是聖錯了
Kawai.
川合
I don't hate your true thoughts.
我並不討厭你說真心話
Yes, Hijiri was wrong.
是，小聖確實錯了
But that's how it is.
但事情就是如此
When you fall for someone, there's no right or wrong.
喜歡上一個人無關對錯
It doesn't matter if it's real or destined either.
是不是真愛，是不是命運都無所謂
You just love them.
就是喜歡
It's hopeless attraction.
無法控制地互相吸引
That's love.
這就是戀愛
Poor Hijiri.
小聖真可憐
All alone in an unfamiliar city, not even knowing he came.
一個人在陌生的地方 不知道他曾經去找她
Imagining how hard she's working, I feel bad for her.
努力當個老師的小聖 想到這裡就覺得有點心疼
Makes me want to
真想飛奔過去
go give her a hug.
給她一個擁抱
What?
什麼？
That's how I am.
這就是我的性格
Kawai, the way things are going, do you see us working out?
川合，這樣我們能順利走下去嗎？
Akira.
阿晶
Welcome home.
歡迎回家
Wait, Akira!
等一下，阿晶！
Hey!
喂！
It's late, why don't you stay the night.
今天已經很晚了，你就住下來吧
You saw your room, didn't you?
你看到你房間了吧？
I left it the way it was.
我完全沒有動
You can come home whenever you want.
所以你隨時都可以回來
This is your home after all.
這裡畢竟是你的家
APRIL 2015, MY NEW CLASS TEACHER WAS HIJIRI.
（2015年4月 聖是我的新班導）
MAY 2015, I TRY TO COMMUNICATE SOMETHING AND SELF-DESTRUCT.
（2015年5月 想要傳達心意而自我毀滅）
HIJIRI
（聖）
MS. SUENAGA, BACK THEN I WAS A LITTLE CRAZY.
（老師，當時我的思緒十分混亂）
IF ONLY I WASN'T 15.
（假如我不是十五歲的話）
MR. NOGAMI
（野上老師）
LET'S FOCUS ON ACT TWO FOR TOMORROW'S REHEARSAL.
（明天的練習以第二幕為主吧）
Roger that.
收到
SORRY, THAT WAS A MISTAKE!
（對不起，我傳錯了！）
IT CAME OUT SO WELL
（因為感覺做得很成功）
SO I MEANT TO SAVE IT.
（正要存下來）
SORTY.
（對不起）
-Goodbye, Ms. Hijiri! -Goodbye.
-再見，老師！ -再見！
Hello!
你好！
Bye!
再見！
Good bye, don't run.
再見，不要跑
Goodbye.
再見
Good work today.
今天辛苦了
Why did you call them!
為什麼要通知他們！
-What? -I told you not to!
-什麼？ -我已經叫妳不要了！
-Why Ayano! -Did something happen to her?
-為什麼這麼對彩乃！ -她怎麼了？
They took her away!
他們帶走她了！
My parents sent a car and took Ayano away!
剛才父母家有人開車來 把彩乃帶走了！
Calm down!
請妳冷靜點！
-What's this commotion? -Please stop!
-到底在吵什麼？ -快住手！
You're all liars!
你們全都是騙子！
Pretending to be on my side, but you were lying!
假裝站在我這邊卻滿口謊言！
We're all on your side!
我們都是站在妳這邊的！
I know about it.
我都知道
Ms. Tachibana?
橘小姐？
Ms. Suenaga, you and Mr. Nogami are an item, aren't you?
末永老師，妳跟野上老師在交往吧？
What?
什麼？
I saw you two eating together.
我有看到你們一起在吃飯
-You even went to the next town over. -It's a misunderstanding.
-特地跑到鄰鎮的餐廳 -妳誤會了
And what was that yesterday, an affair?
而且昨天還那樣，是在劈腿嗎？
Bringing over that businessman.
還帶一個上班族男人回家
No, he's an old friend.
不是的，那是我的老朋友
You're no different.
妳明明也很隨便
Your girlfriend's two-timing you and acting all superior.
老師你女友都在劈腿喔 然後還擺出高高在上的樣子
We're not!
我們沒有！
You're being tricked!
野上老師，你被騙了！
No!
不是！
This is just a one-sided crush on my end.
是我自己單方面喜歡末永老師
What?
什麼？
What'd you say?
你剛才說什麼？
Oh, no, really?
唉呀，天啊，真的嗎？
We haven't done anything inappropriate.
我們並沒有做虧心事
And Ms. Suenaga didn't know.
而且末永老師什麼都不知道
I'm the one who called your parents.
是我聯絡妳的父母
I called them when I heard Ayano was locked out.
我聽說彩乃進不了家門 就聯絡了他們
They said they'd take her.
他們說要讓她暫住在那
Grandma, Nana fetched!
奶奶，奈奈會撿球喔！
-I told you not to contact them. -And I warned you too!
-我明明說了不要通知他們 -我也一樣告誡過妳了！
If you neglected Ayano's care again, that I would call your parents.
如果我們又發現妳不照顧女兒 絕對會通知妳父母
I never neglected her!
我沒有不照顧她！
You put her in danger!
等到出事就太遲了！
We can always talk about how we can move forward.
我們一起討論以後該怎麼辦吧
Call me any time.
妳隨時都可以來找我
Unforgivable.
我絕不原諒
If Ayano never comes home again,
如果彩乃再也不能回來
I'll never forgive you!
我絕不會原諒你們！
What is her problem?
她什麼事啊？
What a hypocrite.
真虛偽！
I'm glad he made that call before something happened.
幸好他在發生意外前就先處理
-Yes. -Absolutely.
-對啊 -就是啊
Ayano is often left home alone at night.
聽說彩乃晚上常常一個人在家
It's our job to protect children.
守護孩子的安全也是我們的責任
-That's right. -Maybe I should go talk to her again.
-是啊 -晚一點我再去找她談談吧
More importantly,
更重要的是
has she been harassing you like that for a while now?
之前她是不是也都這樣威脅妳？
Yes.
是的
I'm sure you don't want to be the target of any rumor,
我能體會妳不想傳出閒言閒語的心情
but we need to be firm with parents like her.
可是對這樣的家長就要果斷應對
Please talk to me next time.
下次一定要找我商量
Understood. I'm sorry.
我知道了，對不起
Good.
好
Can you believe the two of them?
沒想到那兩個人…
What's going to happen now?
會怎麼樣呢？
I'm sorry about that.
剛剛真抱歉
But
但是
that's how I feel.
那是我的真心話
I do hope
我想
to date you someday.
跟妳交往
I know you don't think of me that way yet.
我知道妳對我還沒有那種感覺
But maybe
但是可能
we could slowly build something
我們之後能一點點地累積
so someday you might have feelings for me.
讓妳有一天能喜歡上我
I don't need an answer right away.
妳不用現在給我答覆
Just think about it.
請妳考慮一下
Okay.
好
We just got word.
剛剛接到聯絡
-Ayano is missing. -What?
-彩乃不見了 -什麼？
-Excuse me. -Yes?
-不好意思 -是
-Have you seen Ayano Tachibana? -No, I haven't seen Ayano.
-請問妳有沒有見到橘彩乃？ -彩乃？我沒有見到啊
You haven't?
沒有嗎？
Tachibana!
橘同學！
A neighbor saw her leaving alone.
鄰居說有看到她一個人出門
-Maybe she's trying to go home. -Yes.
-也許是想回家吧 -是的
Damn, I can't get a hold of her mother.
不行，她媽媽不接電話
Tachibana.
橘同學
Tachibana?
橘同學？
Excuse me!
不好意思！
Have you seen a little girl around here?
請問妳有沒有 在這附近見到一個小女孩？
Tachibana!
橘同學！
Tachibana.
橘同學
Are you okay?
妳沒事吧？
Thank goodness, we were worried.
太好了，我們好擔心妳
Were you going home?
妳想回家嗎？
Your mom wasn't home?
媽媽不在家，對吧？
I tried to go back to Grandma's,
我本來要回奶奶家
but I got lost.
但是我迷路了
Then this big brother helped me.
然後就遇到這個大哥哥幫助我
Ms. Suenaga!
末永老師！
Thank goodness you found her.
太好了，找到她了
Let's go, Tachibana.
走吧，橘同學
Wait!
等一下！
I can take her.
我送她回去
What?
什麼？
I'll be waiting at the school.
我會在學校等妳
Ready?
好了嗎？
Let's go.
走吧
Later.
一會見
What?
什麼？
Wait, no way, yuck! Hey!
等一下，不會吧，討厭！喂！
Is it a stink bug? It's a stink bug, right?
是椿象嗎？是椿象吧？
No.
不
Stinks.
好臭
Kuroiwa.
黑岩同學
Why are you here?
你怎麼會在這裡？
Well, what are you doing here?
那老師妳為什麼在這？
That little girl said you weren't married.
我聽那小女孩說妳沒有結婚
I thought you got married to that Shotaro guy
我一直以為 妳嫁給那個叫勝太郎的人
and were buying IKEA furniture together.
兩人一起去宜家買傢俱了
Maybe you'd already have a kid, and became a housewife or something.
然後生了孩子 成為了家庭主婦還是什麼
So why are you still teaching?
可是妳為什麼還在當老師呢？
You came this far to ask me that?
你來這裡就為了問我那些嗎？
No, I didn't.
不是
I'm dating Iwasaki now.
我正在跟岩崎交往
She has a good head on her shoulders.
岩崎同學很好，很可靠
Not to say you don't--
我並不是說你不可靠…
Can I…
我可以…
Can I come here again?
可以再來這裡嗎？
What?
什麼？
You're not with that Shotaro guy anymore, right?
妳跟勝太郎分手了吧？
And you're not my teacher anymore, right?
而且妳不是我的班導了吧？
I'm 18 now.
我已經十八歲了
I will break up with Iwasaki.
我會跟岩崎分手
There's no reason I can't come see you, right?
我沒有不能來見妳的理由了吧？
Now I'm…
我現在…
I'm still…
我還是…
the same as on that day.
那個時候的我
Back on that beach after the fireworks festival,
那場煙火大會後，那海邊
still…
仍然…
No matter who is against it,
這次不管誰反對
I will come see you.
我都會來見妳
I will always--
我會一直…
Never come again.
你別再來了
If you come here,
你如果來這裡
I'll have to move away.
我就得搬走了
I have
我還有
students I care about here.
重要的學生們
I can't lose them.
所以我不能失去他們
Never come again.
你不要再來了
You'll miss your last train.
快到最後一班車了
You'll be stuck here.
你會回不去喔
You can borrow my bike.
腳踏車借你
Just park it in front of the station.
你停在車站前就行了
Here.
來
Thanks.
我知道了
HIJIRI, I WANT TO SEE YOU.
（小聖，我想見妳）
I WANT TO SEE YOU. KUROIWA.
（我想見妳，黑岩）
Ms. Suenaga!
末永老師！
What're you doing here?
妳在這裡做什麼？
-Mr. Nogami. -Yes?
-野上老師 -是
Can I give you my answer now?
我可以現在給你答覆嗎？
Of course.
當然可以
Hold on.
等一下
Okay.
好的
If you would have me, maybe we could get to know each other
如果你願意接受我 也許我們可以慢慢互相瞭解
a little bit at a time.
請多指教
Yes!
是！
I would be honored!
我才是，請多指教！
Sorry.
不好意思
Crap, we need to hurry!
糟了，得快點走了！
You're right!
對呀！
Why?
為什麼？
You messed around with your middle school student three years ago?
聽說妳三年前對學生出手？
I'm disappointed.
我很失望
I can't become a good teacher.
我不可能成為好老師
Would you leave this town with me?
要不要跟我一起離開這裡？
Subtitle translation by: Zensho Yamamoto
字幕翻譯：楊易